Guide to the H.M. Tomlinson Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
H. M. Tomlinson collection
1898-1955
GEN MSS 287
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.8
(6 boxes)
Correspondence and writings by and about H. M. Tomlinson. Tomlinson's correspondents include William McFee, James T. Babb, and Eugene Saxon. There is office correspondence and memos from Harper & Brothers' office files relating to Tomlinson, and letters to James T. Babb and John Archer Gee about Tomlinson. Writings include typescript drafts, with corrections, of All Our Yesterdays, Gallion's Reach, as well as autograph manuscripts and typescripts of various essays.
Tomlinson, H. M. (Henry Major), 1873-1958
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ongoing collection of documents acquired by gift and purchase from various sources. Type of accession (gift or purchase) and date of acquisition is noted in the box-and-folder list. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Restricted Fragile Papers, in box 6 and cold storage, may only be consulted with permission of the appropriate curator. Preservation photocopies and copy prints for reference use have been substituted in the main files.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses accessions of single manuscripts and small groups of manuscripts and other papers, by or pertaining to H. M. Tomlinson, which the library has chosen to group and list as an artificial collection. Materials incorporated into the collection prior to July 1997 have been organized into three series. Series I consists of materials that were gifts of James T. Babb, 1942-1968. Series II consists of materials that were a gift of Harper & Brothers. Series III consists of additional materials acquired by gift and purchase from various sources.
Novelists, English -- 20th Century; Publishers and publishing; All our yesterdays; Gallion's reach; McFee, William, 1881-1966; Babb, James T. (James Tinkham), 1899-1968; Saxon, Eugene; Tomlinson, H. M. (Henry Major), 1873-1958; Harper & Brothers -- Archives
- Gift of James T. Babb, Series I
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Gift of James T. Babb, 1942-1968
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - Letters from H. M. Tomlinson
      - ALS to Mr. Austin, South Croydon, 1931 Jun 23 (Box 1, Folder 1)
        Scope and Contents
        Advising him to "cash in" on his travel experiences
      - 4 ALS to James T. Babb, 1928, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 2)
        Chiefly concerning a Tomlinson bibliography, and the disposition of various manuscripts. Mention is made of Joseph Conrad and Thomas Hardy. In the letter of 1953 Jul 16, Tomlinson comments on changing literary standards and expresses surprise at William McFee's literary difficulties in America
      - ALS to Mrs. Bailey, London, 1924 May 5 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - ALS to Mr. Beresford, Abbotsbury, Dorset, 1928 Aug 13 (Box 1, Folder 4)
        On literary matters
      - ALS to Glen Walton Blodgett, London, 1921 Dec (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - 2 ALS to Mrs. Burgess, Croydon, 1931, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 6)
        Mentioning Tidemarks and Waiting for Daylight
      - 2 ALS to H. S. Canby, Croyden, [1933?], 1934 (Box 1, Folder 7)
        Mentioning Hardy at Max Gate, Joseph Conrad, and Snows of Helicon
      - ALS to Mr. Clark, Croyden, 1927 Sep 8 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - ALS to [Edward] Clodd, London, 1921 Mar 15 (Box 1, Folder 9)
        Removed from Tomlinson's The Sea and the Jungle, London, 1913
      - Autograph postcard to Mrs. Edward Clodd (Phyllis Maud Rope Clodd), St. Columb, Cornwall, [1923] Apr 22 (Box 1, Folder 10)
        Removed from Tomlinson's The Sea and the Jungle London, 1913
      - ALS to Mr. Cole, Croyden, 1938 Jul 29 (Box 1, Folder 11)
        Removed from his All Hands, London, 1937
      - ALS to W. Morris Colles, Poplar E., 1899 May 23 (Box 1, Folder 12)
        Asking about MS submitted to Colles
      - 8 ALS to W. H. Dibben, 1931-37 (Box 1, Folder 13)
        On the lower half of the letter of 18 May 1934 there is a letter to James Venn
      - ALS to Havelock Ellis, London, 1921 Jun 20 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - ALS to Evans, Croyden, 1927 Feb 3 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - ALS to J. C. Faunthorpe, London (Box 1, Folder 16)
        Removed from Tomlinson's Old Junk, London, 1918
      - 2 ALS to Ashley Gibson, Croyden, 1927, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - 5 ALS to "My dear Grubb," Croyden, 1924-28 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - ALS to "Harold," London, 1925 May 15 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - Typed copy of a letter to Harry H. Harper, Jr., Croyden, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 20)
        Original letter dated 1929 Nov 2
      - ALS to Miss Hunter, Croyden, 1929 Apr 10 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - ALS to Mr. Joiner, Cleveland, Ohio (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - ALS to Mr. Judge about an error in text [in Gifts of Fortune ], Croyden, 1928 Nov 21 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - ALS to [Harold Joseph?] Laski, London (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - ANS to Mr. Looker, London, 1922 Nov 21 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - ALS to Mr. Lyman, London (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - 5 ALS to William McFee, South Croyden, Abbotsbury, Dorset, 1931-35 (Box 1, Folder 27)
        Mentioning John Livingston Lowes, Thomas Hardy, and matters of general literary interest
      - Autograph postcard to Lewis Melville [i.e. Lewis Saul Benjamin], London (Box 1, Folder 28)
      - ALS to "Kit" [Christopher Morley?], Croyden, 1927 Jan 3 (Box 1, Folder 29)
        About the "Brown Owl story"
      - 4 ALS to Thomas Moult, 1921-30 (Box 1, Folder 30)
        Accompanied by an envelope addressed to Moult, postmarked January 10, 1933
      - ALS to Mr. Munson, Croyden, 1932 Jun 1 (Box 1, Folder 31)
        About reprinting an extract from The Sea and the Jungle
      - ALS to F. C. Owlett, Croyden, 1930 Nov 18 (Box 1, Folder 32)
        Thanking him for a book
      - ALS to Mr. Peacock, Croyden, 1927 Jun 9 (Box 1, Folder 33)
      - 3 ALS to J. Robertson Scott, South Croyden, London, 1934-55 (Box 1, Folder 34)
      - 2 ALS addressed to his mother and "Em;" 2 ALS addresses to his mother, "Em" and "Phil;" 5 ALS addressed to "Em"; various places, 1906-27 (Box 1, Folder 35)
      - 6 ALS and a postcard to James Venn, 1929-34 (Box 1, Folder 36)
        1 ALS is on the lower half of a letter to W. H. Dibben, dated 18 May 1934
      - ALS to Mrs. Venn, Croyden, 1937 Sep 22 (Box 1, Folder 37)
      - ALS to Mr. Wilson, Croyden, 1929 Jul 24 (Box 1, Folder 38)
        Refusing a lecture engagement
      - 2 ALS to Mr. Wynne, Croyden, 1929 Jul 12 (Box 1, Folder 39)
      - ALS to an unidentified correspondent, South Croyden, 1931 Jun 5 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Letters to H. M. Tomlinson
      - Babb, James Tinkham. 3 typed letters (carbons), 1953, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Letters to James T. Babb from Others
      - Canby, Henry Seidel. TLS, New York, 1928 Nov 20 (Box 1, Folder 42)
        Explaining a "mix-up" on a Tomlinson manuscript, and offering a letter instead
      - Hathaway, R. H. TLS, Toronto, 1929 Apr 20 (Box 1, Folder 43)
        Regarding the Toronto publication of Tomlinson's appreciation of Katherine Mansfield
      - Smith, Percy J. 9 TLS and 5 ALS, 1927-33 (Box 1, Folder 44)
        Chiefly about the layouts made by Smith for Tomlinson's All Our Yesterdays and about portraits of Tomlinson. The enclosures are layouts and proofs of All Our Yesterdays
      - Squire, John Collings. TLS, London, 1928 May 10 (Box 1, Folder 45)
        - Regretting that he has no Tomlinson manuscripts, 1928 May 10
      - Tomlinson, H. Charles. TLS, New York, 1930 Dec 8 (Box 1, Folder 46)
        Mentioning Tomlinson, his father, and the Cheshire house series
  - WRITINGS
    - Tomlinson, H. M.
      - "An Attempt at Winter Sports," typescript draft, with a few corrections, [Croyden?], [1929?]
        Accompanied by a layout in pencil for the article, as it was to appear in Nash's Magazine for 1929, and by corrected page proofs of the article, with title: "My Attempt at Winter Sports"
        Related Archival Materials note
        See: Oversize, box 5, folder 114
      - "Cruising in Winter," typescript draft with numerous corrections, signed, South Croyden, [England], [1929]
        Accompanied by corrected page proofs of the article as it was to appear in Nash's Magazine, 1929, with title: "Cruising in winter among the islands that never alter"
        Related Materials
        See: Oversize, box 5, folder 115
      - "The Gaffer," corrected page proof of the article as it was to appear in Nash's Magazine, 1930. Stamped 7 Jan. 1930
        See: Oversize, box 5, folder 116
      - "The Gaffer," typescript draft, with several corrections, [1930]
        Accompanied by a layout in pencil of the article as it was to appear in Nash's Magazine for 1930, and by page proofs, corrected. Accompanied by an ALS from Tomlinson to Mr. Glenton-Kerr, forwarding the proof of "The Gaffer" Rigewood, Jan. 8, 1930. Laid in, a photograph of Tomlinson by Howard Coster
        See: Oversize, box 5, folder 117
      - "Granada," autograph manuscript, signed, of a travel essay, with numerous changes in the author's hand. Written in pencil and ink, Croyden, England (Box 1, Folder 47)
      - "A History of Lloyd's," by Charles Wright & Ernest Fayle. Manuscript review by H.M. Tomlinson, with numerous corrections, Croyden, England, [1928] (Box 1, Folder 48)
      - Empty folder (Box 1, Folder 49)
      - "Joseph Conrad," page proof, corrected by the author, of the article as it was to appear in The Saturday Review of Literature v.4, No. 12, Oct. 15, 1927
        See: Oversize, box 5, folder 118
      - "Obituary," autograph manuscript of an imaginary obituary of himself, Abbotsbury, Dorset, [1942 May 8] (Box 1, Folder 50)
      - "The Prelude," typescript draft of an essay on Joseph Conrad, with the author's corrections, Croyden, [England] (Box 1, Folder 51)
        Accompanied by a TLS from G. T. Keating to J. T. Babb, transmitting the MS to him. New York, June 10, 1938
      - "Sergeant Grischa," typewritten review, signed, of the novel by Arnold Zweig, with MS corrections by the author, Croyden, England, [1928?] (Box 1, Folder 52)
        Addressed to H. S. Canby. Accompanied by a TLS from H. S. Canby to James T. Babb, transmitting the manuscript to him, dated New York, Jan 25, 1929
      - "Thomas Hardy," typewritten draft with the author's corrections, and a final paragraph in his hand, [1928] (Box 1, Folder 53)
        Accompanied by the corrected proof of the essay as it was to appear in The Saturday Review of Literature v. 4, No. 29, February 11, 1929
        See also: Oversize, box 5, folder 119
      - "A Typhoidal Diary. Extracts from a New Diary of a Plague," autograph manuscript signed "by Croham Hurst," Croydon (Box 1, Folder 54)
        Together with ALS to "The Editor, Daily Herald," concerning the above
      - Note about what the sea had meant to him, signed and written on the verso of a TLS from Wilfred Whitten and George Blake, editors of John O'London's Weekly, London, 1924 May 23 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Writings by Others
      - Bennett, Arnold. Autograph manuscript review of H. M. Tomlinson's Gallion's Reach, with title "Books & Persons", 1927 Aug 5 (Box 1, Folder 56)
        Compares Tomlinson and Joseph Conrad
      - Prokosch, Frederic. Check list of Henry Major Tomlinson, with annotations by Tomlinson, to whom the list had been submitted, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 57)
- Gift of Harper & Brothers, Series II
  Gift of Harper & Brothers, 1963
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - Harper & Brothers office correspondence: H. M. Tomlinson file, including letters to and from Tomlinson, internal letters and memos about Tomlinson
      - Correspondence, 1927-29 (Box 2, Folder 58)
      - Correspondence, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 59)
      - Correspondence, 1931-33 (Box 2, Folder 60)
      - Correspondence, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 61)
      - Correspondence, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 62)
      - Correspondence, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 63-64)
      - Correspondence, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 65-70)
        See also: Oversize, box 5, folder 120
      - Correspondence, 1938-40 (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - Tomlinson, H. M. ALS to Norman Douglas, 1926 Jul 1 (Box 2, Folder 72)
      Introducing Eugene Saxon
    - Tomlinson, H. M. 34 ALS to Eugene Saxon, 1926-[41] (Box 2, Folder 73-76)
      See also: Harper & Brothers correspondence, Box 5, folder 120
  - WRITINGS AND OTHER PAPERS
    - All Our Yesterdays, autograph manuscript draft of introduction, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 77)
    - All Our Yesterdays, typescript and typescript carbon, corrected (Box 3, Folder 78-87)
    - Gallion's Reach, typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 88-95)
    - Photographs of Tomlinson, [1932] (Box 4, Folder 96)
- Additional Materials, Series III
  Other materials acquired from various sources
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - Letters by H. M. Tomlinson
      - ALS to William Morris Colles, Poplar E., 1898 Aug 18 (Box 4, Folder 97)
        Gift, 1944
      - ANS to William Morris Colles, Poplar, 1899 Jan 5 (Box 4, Folder 98)
        Purchase, 1954
      - 2 ALS to Norman Douglas, London, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 99)
      - ALS to Mr. Gaige, Abbotsbury, Dorset, 1928 Aug 30 (Box 4, Folder 100)
      - 3 ALS to John Archer Gee, Croyden, 1930-34 (Box 4, Folder 101)
      - ALS to William McFee, Dorset, England, 1953 Aug 12 (Box 4, Folder 102)
        Gift, 1953
      - ALS to "My dear Ranee," Croydon, 1928 Jan 23 (Box 4, Folder 103)
        Mentions Sir James Brooke, Sir Stamford Raffles, and Thomas Hardy
      - 5 ALS to his sister "Em" (Emily Tomlinson), various places, 1923-27 (Box 4, Folder 104)
        The letter of Oct. 17, 1927 is accompanied by an oak leaf from Walden Pond, with Tomlinson's autograph and the date of Oct. 16, 1927. Gift, 1944
      - ALS to "Mother, Em & Phil, and Jim," Phillipville, Algeria, 1926 Dec 17 (Box 4, Folder 105)
      - ALS to his son, Henry C. Tomlinson, Croydon, 1928 May 5 (Box 4, Folder 106)
        Purchase, 1973
      - ALS to Mr. Wilson, Croydon, Surrey, 1927 Nov 22 (Box 4, Folder 107)
    - Letters by Others to Others
      - Canby, Henry Seidel. TLS to John Archer Gee, New York, 1931 Feb 25 (Box 4, Folder 108)
        Accompanied by a clipping of John Archer Gee's review of "Out of Soundings" by Tomlinson, which appeared in The Saturday Review of Literature for March 21, 1931
        See also: Oversize, box 5, folder 121
      - Purdy, Richard Little. ALS to John Archer Gee, Dorchester, 1933 Jul 8 (Box 4, Folder 109)
      - Tomlinson, H. Charles. TLS to John Archer Gee, New York City, 1931 Feb 14 (Box 4, Folder 110)
  - WRITINGS
    - Tomlinson, H. M. "The Estuary," typescript [carbon] with manuscript corrections, London (Box 4, Folder 111)
      Purchase, 1982
    - Tomlinson, H. M. "The Lower Reaches," typescript with manuscript corrections signed by the author, London (Box 4, Folder 112)
    - Gee, John Archer. "Henry Major Tomlinson," typescript of an untitled lecture on H. M. Tomlinson, signed and corrected. (Box 4, Folder 113)
      Mr. Tomlinson, to whom this manuscript was submitted, has added numerous marginal notes and comments. Accompanied by an envelope addressed by Tomlinson to J. A. Gee, and a photograph of Tomlinson. Gift, 1944
- Oversize, [1929?]
  - Tomlinson, H. M. "An Attempt at Winter Sports," typescript draft, with a few corrections, [Croyden?] (from series I), [1929?] (Box 5, Folder 114)
  - Tomlinson, H. M. "Cruising in Winter," typescript draft with numerous corrections, signed, South Croyden, [England] (from series I), [1929] (Box 5, Folder 115)
  - Tomlinson, H. M. "The Gaffer," corrected page proof of the article as it was to appear in Nash's Magazine, 1930. Stamped 7 Jan. 1930 (from series I) (Box 5, Folder 116)
  - Tomlinson, H. M. "The Gaffer," typescript draft, with several corrections (from series I), [1930] (Box 5, Folder 117)
  - Tomlinson, H. M. "Joseph Conrad," page proof, corrected by the author, of the article as it was to appear in The Saturday Review of Literature v.4, No. 12, Oct. 15, 1927 (from series I) (Box 5, Folder 118)
  - Tomlinson, H. M. "Thomas Hardy," typewritten draft with the author's corrections, and a final paragraph in his hand (from series I), [1928] (Box 5, Folder 119)
  - Harper and Brothers correspondence (from series II), 1937 (Box 5, Folder 120)
  - Canby, Henry Seidel. TLS to John Archer Gee, New York (from series III), 1931 Feb 25 (Box 5, Folder 121)
    Accompanied by a clipping of John Archer Gee's review of "Out of Soundings" by Tomlinson, which appeared in The Saturday Review of Literature for March 21, 1931 Gift, 1944
- Restricted Fragile Materials
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 2, folders 59, 63-64 (Box 6, Folder 122)
  - Box 2, folders 65-66, 69, 75 (Box 6, Folder 123)
  - Box 4, folder 95 (Box 6, Folder 124)
  - Box 2, folder 58 (Box cs, Folder 125)